<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://bridgetownrb.com/" version="1.3.4">Bridgetown</generator><link href="https://falsetrue.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://falsetrue.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-25T13:42:07+02:00</updated><id>https://falsetrue.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">FalseTrue</title><subtitle>Scripts of cyberdaemon</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Рассказ - “Нужно продолжать работать”</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/tales/2024/10/11/crysis-tale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Рассказ - &quot;Нужно продолжать работать&quot;" /><published>2024-10-11T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-11T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-10-10-crysis-tale.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/tales/2024/10/11/crysis-tale/">&lt;p&gt;Он сидел у тусклого экрана, голова низко опущена, руки безвольно лежали на клавиатуре. Весь код — бесконечные строки цифр и символов, олицетворение порядка и логики, — сегодня казался ему каким-то особенным издевательством. Андрей Павлович, программист с десятилетним стажем, давно разучился испытывать что-то иное, кроме глубокой, неизбывной усталости. Не физической — нет, это была усталость иного рода, тягучая, тяжелая, словно гиря, привязанная к его мыслям и чувствам. Эта усталость прорастала в его душе как сорняк, поглощая все вокруг.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Тупость процессов, с которой он сталкивался день за днем, словно темный туман окружала его со всех сторон. “Кто это придумал? Кто сделал так, что мы погружаемся в этот бесконечный хаос, когда каждый правит по своему, но ничего не работает?” — думал он, глядя на свое отражение в мониторе. Не отражение человека, а отражение усталого существа, измученного непрерывной борьбой с бессмысленностью.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Андрей Павлович знал, что причина его страданий — не код. Код был честным, прямым, логичным. Он создавал иллюзию порядка в этом мире хаоса, но стоило выйти за пределы этой микроскопической вселенной, как начиналась нескончаемая путаница людей, процессов, решений, которые ничего не значат.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Как он ненавидел эти ежедневные собрания, где решения принимались не теми, кто понимает, а теми, кто просто говорит громче других. Каждый раз, когда кто-то с важным видом предлагал очередную нелепицу, Андрей Павлович с трудом сдерживал горький смех. Они говорили об оптимизации, о новых методологиях, о том, как сделать всё быстрее и проще. Но разве кто-то из них знал, что такое истинная простота? Разве кто-то видел код так, как он?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;«Мы тонем в собственной некомпетентности, и самое страшное — все делают вид, что так и должно быть», — думал он, чувствуя, как отчаяние медленно, но верно, заполняет всё его существо.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Его взгляд остановился на строчке кода, который он написал сегодня утром. «Какая же это пустота», — подумал он. Это была не просто пустота рабочего процесса, не пустота написанного им кода — это была пустота самого существования, в которой не осталось ни смысла, ни цели. Ведь сколько бы он ни старался, мир всё равно останется таким же глупым и несуразным, полным нелепых решений и бессмысленных процессов.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Внутри него разгорался тихий огонь протеста, но он знал, что этот огонь никогда не вырвется наружу. Все вокруг него были частью системы, которая никогда не изменится. Этот абсурд, эти тупые процессы были частью жизни, и Андрей Павлович не мог с ними бороться. Он был только свидетелем, беспомощным наблюдателем своей жизни, погруженной в хаос чужой бездумности.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ну что ж”, — подумал он наконец, глядя на черный экран перед собой. “Нужно продолжать работать”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tale" /><category term="ru" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing LetsEncrypt with Kubernetes on Digital Ocean</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/howto/2024/10/07/kubernetes-letsencrypt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing LetsEncrypt with Kubernetes on Digital Ocean" /><published>2024-10-07T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-10-07-kubernetes-letsencrypt.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/howto/2024/10/07/kubernetes-letsencrypt/">&lt;p&gt;If expeirience working with Kubernetes on Digital Ocean and you need to install or renew LetsEncrypt certificate you might be struggled with in update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To manage certificate there is a special tool called &lt;strong&gt;cert-manager&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://cert-manager.io&quot;&gt;https://cert-manager.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works-&quot;&gt;How it works ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;    +----------------+           +---------------------+           +--------------------+           +---------------------------+
    | Let&apos;s Encrypt  |           |  cert-manager       |           | Ingress Controller |           |   cert-manager            |
    |    (ACME)      |           |  (k8s)              |           |     (Nginx)        |           |   k8s:cm-acme-http-solver |
    +----------------+           +---------------------+           +--------------------+           +---------------------------+
          |                             |                               |                            |
          | 1. Create CertificateRequest|                               |                            |
          |&amp;lt;--------------------------- |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             | 2. Request HTTP-01 Challenge  |                            |
          |                             |------------------------------&amp;gt;|                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |  3. Serve challenge file   |
          |                             |&amp;lt;------------------------------|----------------------------|
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          | 4. Validate Challenge       |                               |                            |
          |&amp;lt;----------------------------|                               |                            |
          |                             |                               |                            |
          | 5. Issue Certificate        | cert-manager                  |                            |
          |----------------------------&amp;gt;| Stores certificate in Secrets |                            |
          |                             | allowing access it for Nginx  |                            |

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cert-Manager requesting letsencrypt to issue new ceritificate, LetsEncrypt verify generated certificate using various types of challenges&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s Encrypt supports several challenge types that allow it to verify ownership of a domain before issuing SSL/TLS certificates. These challenges are part of the ACME (Automated Certificate Management Environment) protocol, which is used by Let’s Encrypt and other ACME-compatible certificate authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the three main types of Let’s Encrypt challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;http-01-challenge&quot;&gt;HTTP-01 Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HTTP-01 challenge requires the web server that serves your domain to respond to an HTTP request at a specific path. The cert-manager or your ACME client will provision a file at the path .well-known/acme-challenge/ on your server that contains a token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s Encrypt asks you to serve a token from http://your-domain/.well-known/acme-challenge/&lt;token&gt;.&lt;/token&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ACME client (e.g., cert-manager) responds to this request by provisioning the token on your web server (usually through an Ingress controller or a pod).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s Encrypt validates the challenge by making an HTTP GET request to the token URL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best for: Domains with direct access to HTTP traffic. This is commonly used with Kubernetes Ingress controllers like NGINX.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requirements: Port 80 must be open and reachable on your server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dns-01-challenge&quot;&gt;DNS-01 Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DNS-01 challenge requires you to prove domain ownership by creating a DNS TXT record with a specific token. The cert-manager or your ACME client will automate this by updating your DNS provider’s records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s Encrypt asks you to create a DNS TXT record _acme-challenge.your-domain with a specific value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ACME client (e.g., cert-manager) interacts with your DNS provider’s API to create this record automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s Encrypt queries your domain’s DNS TXT record to verify that it contains the correct value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best for: Wildcard certificates (e.g., *.example.com), internal services, and domains where direct HTTP access is not possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requirements: You must have control over the domain’s DNS records, and your DNS provider must support automation via an API that the ACME client can use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tls-alpn-01-challenge&quot;&gt;TLS-ALPN-01 Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TLS-ALPN-01 challenge allows validation over a custom TLS extension called ALPN (Application-Layer Protocol Negotiation). This challenge type is specifically for cases where you have control over the server’s TLS configuration and don’t want to use HTTP or DNS-based validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ACME client (e.g., cert-manager) configures your web server to respond to TLS connections with a special ALPN protocol (acme-tls/1) and a certificate containing the challenge token.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s Encrypt connects to your server over HTTPS and validates the challenge by verifying the presence of this certificate using the ALPN protocol.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best for: Environments with strict security policies where serving files over HTTP is not an option or where DNS automation is not available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requirements: You must have control over the TLS configuration and be able to install the custom certificate temporarily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Challenge&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Best Use Case&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Requirements&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTTP-01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Serve a token over HTTP on port 80.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Simple web domains with HTTP access.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Port 80 open and accessible.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS-01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Create a DNS TXT record with the token.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wildcard certificates and internal domains.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;DNS provider with API for automation.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLS-ALPN-01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Respond to a TLS connection with a token via ALPN.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Strict security environments.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Control over TLS configuration.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary-of-the-process&quot;&gt;Summary of the Process:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingress Resource: You define an Ingress resource that cert-manager observes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Certificate Request: cert-manager issues a request to Let’s Encrypt.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ACME Challenge: cert-manager fulfills the HTTP-01 or DNS-01 challenge to prove domain ownership.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Challenge Validation: Let’s Encrypt validates the challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Certificate Issuance: Let’s Encrypt issues the certificate, and cert-manager stores it as a Kubernetes Secret.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ingress Controller: The Ingress controller terminates TLS for incoming HTTPS traffic using the issued certificate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automated Renewal: cert-manager automatically renews certificates before they expire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DNS-01&lt;/code&gt; requires api access to change DNS configuration, which is why everybody uses HTTP-01 challenge which is just a request of a created file on server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;install&quot;&gt;Install&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a few ways to install &lt;strong&gt;cert-manager&lt;/strong&gt;, one of them is directly with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kubectl apply -f ...&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kubectl apply -f https://github.com/cert-manager/cert-manager/releases/download/v1.16.0/cert-manager.yaml`
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;strong&gt;JetStack&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;helm repo add jetstack https://charts.jetstack.io --force-update
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;strong&gt;cert-manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;helm install cert-manager jetstack/cert-manager \ 
    --namespace cert-manager \ 
    --create-namespace \ 
    -version v1.16.0 \ 
    --set crds.enabled=true
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verify installation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kubectl get pods -n cert-manager
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-issue&quot;&gt;The Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem starts here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cmd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kubectl logs -l app=cert-manager -n cert-manager -f
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;E1006 23:14:38.1433441 sync.go:208] &quot;propagation check failed&quot; err=&quot;failed to perform self check GET request &apos;http://example.com/.well-known/acme-challenge/&amp;lt;token&amp;gt;&apos;: Get \&quot;http://example.com/.well-known/acme-challenge/&amp;lt;token&amp;gt;\&quot;: EOF&quot; logger=&quot;cert-manager.controller&quot; resource_name=&quot;example-com-tls-1-622117757-218251542&quot; resource_namespace=&quot;default&quot; resource_kind=&quot;Challenge&quot; resource_version=&quot;v1&quot; dnsName=&quot;example.com&quot; type=&quot;HTTP-01&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the cert-manager cannot access the challenge file to verify, at the same time if I go to **http://example.com/.well-known/acme-challenge/&lt;token&gt;** with the browser it will be open without a problem.&lt;/token&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-is-that-&quot;&gt;Why is that ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;

In this case, Kubernetes networking is too smart for its own good. See upstream Kubernetes issue

An ingress controller service deploys a LoadBalancer, which is provisioned by your cloud provider. 
Kubernetes notices the LoadBalancer&apos;s external IP address. As an &quot;optimization&quot;, kube-proxy on 
each node writes iptables rules that rewrite all outbound traffic to the LoadBalancer&apos;s external 
IP address to instead be redirected to the cluster-internal Service ClusterIP address. If your 
cloud load balancer doesn&apos;t modify the traffic, then indeed this is a helpful optimization.

However, when you have the PROXY protocol enabled, the external load balancer does modify the 
traffic, prepending the PROXY line before each TCP connection. If you connect directly to the 
web server internally, bypassing the external load balancer, then it will receive traffic 
without the PROXY line. In the case of ingress-nginx with use-proxy-protocol: &quot;true&quot;, you&apos;ll 
find that NGINX fails when receiving a bare GET request. As a result, 
accessing http://subdomain.example.com/ from inside the cluster fails!

This is particularly a problem when using cert-manager for provisioning SSL certificates. 
Cert-manager uses HTTP01 validation, and before asking LetsEncrypt to hit 
http://subdomain.example.com/.well-known/acme-challenge/some-special-code, 
it tries to access this URL itself as a self-check. This fails. Cert-manager does not 
allow you to skip the self-check. 
As a result, your certificate is never provisioned, even though the verification URL would 
be perfectly accessible externally. See upstream cert-manager issues: proxy_protocol 
mode breaks HTTP01 challenge Check stage, http-01 self check failed for domain, Self check always fail

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;There are several ways to solve this problem:

    Modify Kubernetes to not rewrite the external IP address of a LoadBalancer.
    Modify nginx to treat the PROXY line as optional.
    Modify cert-manager to add the PROXY line on its self-check.
    Modify cert-manager to bypass the self-check.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully to &lt;a href=&quot;@compumike&quot;&gt;https://github.com/compumike/&lt;/a&gt; there is a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;hairpin-proxy&quot;&gt;https://github.com/compumike/hairpin-proxy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need to do in case of such problem is to installed into your k8s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kubectl apply -f https://raw.githubusercontent.com/compumike/hairpin-proxy/v0.2.1/deploy.yml 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will setup bypass access for ACME challenge, and certificates will be validated properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cert-manager.io&quot;&gt;https://cert-manager.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/compumike/hairpin-proxy&quot;&gt;https://github.com/compumike/hairpin-proxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org/&quot;&gt;https://letsencrypt.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="software" /><category term="kubernetes" /><category term="linux" /><category term="security" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My comment on linkedin collected almost thousand of likes</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/09/30/linked-comment-rush/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My comment on linkedin collected almost thousand of likes" /><published>2024-09-30T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-09-30-linked-comment-rush.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/09/30/linked-comment-rush/">&lt;p&gt;My comment on linkedin post for some guy, collected almost thousand of likes. “¯_(ツ)_/¯”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/linkedin-1000-likes.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7243514747634040832?commentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7243514747634040832%2C7243527220693000193%29&amp;amp;dashCommentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afsd_comment%3A%287243527220693000193%2Curn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A7243514747634040832%29&quot;&gt;Thread on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="software" /><category term="linkedin" /></entry><entry><title type="html">EuRuKo 2024 Review</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/note/2024/09/15/euruko2024-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EuRuKo 2024 Review" /><published>2024-09-15T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-09-15-euruko2024-review.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/note/2024/09/15/euruko2024-review/">&lt;p&gt;EuRuKo 2024 reivew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it is EuRuKo ? It is the conference about programming language&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
EuRuKo is a Ruby conference organised annually, each year in a different European city chosen by the participants.

Every year the Ruby community from Europe and beyond come to EuRuKo to meet and share their love of Ruby. This is is the longest running and biggest Ruby conference anywhere in Europe and one of the biggest in the world.

It’s up to the participants to pick the next city where the conference will be held. Attendees will pitch their own cities to be the hosts of the next year’s conference which are then voted on by the audience. This also means that the conference organisers will change every year.

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://euruko.org/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here it is EuRuKo 2024. This year it Was set in Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Positioned as greatest ruby conference&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participation of ruby creators and contributors - Yukihiro “Matz” Matsumoto, Xavier Noria, Koichi Sasada, Dave Thomas, Samuel Giddins, and many more&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location with a good food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Splitted to 3 tracks (first time for this conference), but its obvious better to have 1 strong sequences of speaches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of variety of sponsorships signifies that conference has no marketing interest among software development market.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No drinking water supply (reminder: conference was paid)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feels like speeches was not correlate with the majority of audience professional experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;Plot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT conferences nowadays are becoming more and more like casual, recreational, entertainment events rather than events where you can gain knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall&quot;&gt;Overall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My score for this conference is 3/5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;flex gap-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/EuRuKo2024/EuRuKo2024-1.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/EuRuKo2024/EuRuKo2024-2.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/EuRuKo2024/EuRuKo2024-3.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/EuRuKo2024/EuRuKo2024-4.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://euruko.org&quot;&gt;https://euruko.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://2024.euruko.org&quot;&gt;https://2024.euruko.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/company/euruko/posts/?feedView=all&quot;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/company/euruko/posts/?feedView=all&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="review" /><category term="event" /><category term="ruby" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Agile manifesto failure</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/09/10/agile-manifesto-failure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Agile manifesto failure" /><published>2024-09-10T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-10T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-09-10-agile-manifesto-failure.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/09/10/agile-manifesto-failure/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
My favourite part here is: “Working software over comprehensive documentation.” People often interpret this as “We don’t need documentation, we need working software,” which can lead to a situation where they end up with neither documentation nor working software. When a new developer comes along and asks, “Where’s the documentation I can quickly review?” they are usually pointed back to that initial quote, with the added comment, “We are agile”. This demonstrates how the meaning of highly compressed quotes can be blindly extracted, often leading to a completely different, almost opposite interpretation.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/michaelkuesters_agile-agile-softwaredevelopment-activity-7238922044107558914-iAtv?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&quot;&gt;Discussion on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="agile" /><category term="linkedin" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mantis</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/photo/2024/09/08/mantis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mantis" /><published>2024-09-08T11:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T11:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-09-08-mantis.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/photo/2024/09/08/mantis/">&lt;div class=&quot;ft-picture-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photography_copyrighted/Animals/Mantis.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-img&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&quot;Mantis&quot; // 2024-09-08 &amp;copy; Dmitry Ro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;ft-picture-info&quot;&gt;FUJIFILM XT-4 | XF16-80mmF4 R OIS WR | 80mm | F/4 | 1/2000 | ISO 500 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photo" /><category term="animals" /><category term="insects" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ferrari 308 GTB</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/photo/2024/09/01/ferrari-308gtb/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ferrari 308 GTB" /><published>2024-09-01T11:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T11:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-09-01-ferrari-308GTB.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/photo/2024/09/01/ferrari-308gtb/">&lt;div class=&quot;ft-picture-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photography_copyrighted/Cars/Ferrari308GTBFront.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-img&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&quot;Ferrari 308 GTB Front&quot; // 2024-09-01 &amp;copy; Dmitry Ro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;ft-picture-info&quot;&gt;FUJIFILM XT-4 | XF16-80mmF4 R OIS WR | 29m | F/5.6 | 1/250 | ISO 160 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ft-picture-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photography_copyrighted/Cars/Ferrari308GTBRear.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-img&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&quot;Ferrari 308 GTB Rear&quot; // 2024-09-01 &amp;copy; Dmitry Ro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;ft-picture-info&quot;&gt;FUJIFILM XT-4 | XF16-80mmF4 R OIS WR | 29m | F/5.6 | 1/250 | ISO 160 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ft-picture-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photography_copyrighted/Cars/Ferrari308GTBCockpit.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-img&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&quot;Ferrari 308 GTB Cockpit&quot; // 2024-09-01 &amp;copy; Dmitry Ro.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class=&quot;ft-picture-info&quot;&gt;FUJIFILM XT-4 | XF16-80mmF4 R OIS WR | 29m | F/5.6 | 1/250 | ISO 160 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="photo" /><category term="car" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why big company experience doesn’t always translate to practical skills</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/08/31/big-companies-hoax/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why big company experience doesn&apos;t always translate to practical skills" /><published>2024-08-31T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-08-31-big-companies-hoax.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/comment/2024/08/31/big-companies-hoax/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
Many think they will work for big companies to gain experience, but they don’t realize that this experience involves solving problems that don’t exist outside of the big company. That experience will not help you do real work &quot;in the field&quot;. This is also a pattern that brings various technologies into smaller businesses that have no clue why they need them. They propose using these technologies without understanding that they were designed to solve specific problems that only exist at certain scales.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7235182991822499840?commentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Acomment%3A%28activity%3A7235182991822499840%2C7235188155887300608%29&amp;amp;dashCommentUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afsd_comment%3A%287235188155887300608%2Curn%3Ali%3Aactivity%3A7235182991822499840%29&quot;&gt;Discussion on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got a recommendation on this subject in this thread, the book “Siliconned” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://emaggiori.com/&quot;&gt;Emmanuel Maggori&lt;/a&gt;.
Will be on my bookshelf soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/siliconned.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-img&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="humanity" /><category term="modernity" /><category term="books" /><category term="linkedin" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Debian turned 31 years old</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/share/2024/08/18/debian-31/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Debian turned 31 years old" /><published>2024-08-18T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-18T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-08-18-debian-31.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/share/2024/08/18/debian-31/">&lt;div class=&quot;flex&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;justify-middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/debian-31th_DLenharo_300x350.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bits.debian.org/2024/08/debian-turns-31.html&quot;&gt;https://bits.debian.org/2024/08/debian-turns-31.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debian is my favourite Linux distrubution, I am using it since version 2.2 Potato, and now it turns 31 years. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debian.org/releases/&quot;&gt;https://www.debian.org/releases/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/DebianLogo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;/assets/images/DebianLogo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://falsetrue.io/link/2023/08/16/debian-30/&quot;&gt;https://falsetrue.io/link/2023/08/16/debian-30/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux" /><category term="scene" /><category term="history" /><category term="debian" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">In memory of Terry Davis</title><link href="https://falsetrue.io/person/2024/08/14/terry-davis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In memory of Terry Davis" /><published>2024-08-14T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>repo://posts.collection/_posts/2024-08-14-terry-davis.markdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://falsetrue.io/person/2024/08/14/terry-davis/">&lt;p&gt;In memory of &lt;b&gt;Terry Davis&lt;/b&gt; &lt;em&gt;(December 15, 1969 – August 11, 2018)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;ft-persona-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/TerryDavisPortrait.jpg&quot; class=&quot;ft-persona&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;&quot;&gt;
        Terry Davis - &quot;Smartest programmer that ever lived&quot;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@terrydavisoldarchive5371/videos&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeos.org/&quot;&gt;TempleOS&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/TerryDavis.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/TerryDavisWithMonitor.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terry A. Davis was a singular figure in the world of software development, known for creating TempleOS, a highly unconventional operating system that he developed entirely by himself. Davis was both a brilliant programmer and a deeply troubled individual, battling schizophrenia throughout much of his life, which heavily influenced both his work and his worldview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TempleOS was Davis’ magnum opus, a 64-bit operating system with a unique vision. Designed to be a modern-day temple where God could communicate with humans, it featured a deliberately limited resolution of 640x480 and a text-based interface with a custom programming language, HolyC, which Davis also wrote from scratch. The system was lightweight, with its design focused on simplicity, speed, and direct communication with hardware, breaking away from modern OS standards. Despite being rough around the edges, TempleOS was a testament to Davis’ raw talent and determination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davis’ creation, however, was deeply intertwined with his mental health struggles. His schizophrenia led him to believe that God was directly guiding his work, and much of TempleOS’s structure and aesthetic choices reflected his religious visions. Although many in the tech community found his work difficult to categorize, it was impossible not to recognize the genius behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terry Davis’ life and work have sparked conversations about mental health in the tech world. He demonstrated the vast potential of a lone programmer driven by passion and belief, yet his story also highlighted the profound challenges of working with untreated mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He passed away on 11 of August in 2018 (was hit by train), but his legacy continues to resonate with programmers and creators, serving as a reminder of the complexity of human genius and the fine line between creativity and struggle. TempleOS, though niche, remains a fascinating relic of one man’s uncompromising vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://templeos.org/&quot;&gt;TempleOS&lt;/a&gt; - The TempleOS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cia-foundation/TempleOS&quot;&gt;TempleOS source code&lt;/a&gt; - The TempleOS source code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://holyc-lang.com/&quot;&gt;HolyC programming language&lt;/a&gt; - programming language that Terry Davis invented to write TempleOS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minexew/Shrine&quot;&gt;Srine&lt;/a&gt; - fork of TemplateOS with Networking, and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Zeal-Operating-System/ZealOS&quot;&gt;ZealOS&lt;/a&gt; - Another work with enchancements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tinkeros/TinkerOS&quot;&gt;TinkerOS&lt;/a&gt; - another fork&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bbrfoundation.donordrive.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=donorDrive.personalCampaign&amp;amp;participantID=8191&quot;&gt;A personal campaign sponsored by Family and Friends of Terry Donations to Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/192900656/terrence_andrew-davis&quot;&gt;Find a Grave&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/terry-a-davis/&quot;&gt;Terry Davis Linkedin Tribute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;good-videos-with-covering-his-story&quot;&gt;Good videos with covering his story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YMUhbIAA9-8&quot;&gt;The Schizophrenic Genius - Terry A. Davis Story&lt;/a&gt; - the good coverage of Terrys story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cyz08j7EchY&quot;&gt;The Apostles Keeping TEMPLEOS Alive…&lt;/a&gt; - talks about the details and forks of the Temple OS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oY33uoBSw3w?si=AF6ZfxJvHGi3cBto&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the memory of Terry Davis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hmjU-6tkEc8?si=e0Gjtrja2AR7-TkR&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="person" /><category term="famouse" /><category term="hacker" /><category term="scene" /><category term="legacy" /></entry></feed>